[Music]
hi my name is stepan B and I'm from the
developer tools team in business Central
for the next few minutes I'm going to go
through some of the language changes
that had happened in the 2024 Wave 2
release I'm not going to go into detail
with all the different changes there are
other sessions for that but I am going
to give you that overview so you can
quickly dive into the things that
interest you
most we have quite some things to cover
so let's Dive Right into our favorite
tool vs code so the first thing I want
to talk about is tables let's look at
what changed in
tables so on tables you'll Now find a
new property for Fields that's called
optimized for text
search the idea is that you can specify
which Fields should be indexed for
optimized text
search you can find the same information
about the field in the field ref so you
have have the is optimized for search
property and in the fields record you
can find the optimized for search
property
also moving on let's start with
something that you cannot use so there's
a new page type called configuration
dialogue it's part of our AI investment
for now you cannot use it until we get
this done you cannot use it but you'll
see it in the code and you might try to
use it and get this kind of error so
here you see the feature is under
development and cannot be used we hope
to see it live very soon moving
on so you'll Now find also that on pages
on more pages than before on the card
Pages list plus pages and document Pages
you can use the prompting actions
allowing you to showcase the nice uh
co-pilot features that you have created
in the different card
Types on pages you can also use the
style enum the page style enum the page
style enum is a way for us to get away
from these hardcoded favorable
unfavorable and so forth style
Expressions you can use
the page style like this you have a a
format of a certain page style and then
that goes into a variable that you put
on the
field the value of the sty expression
still needs to be a string because it is
an expression but now you don't have to
have these labels lying
around very
good profile extensions you can now
extend
profiles with additional customizations
if you want to allowing you to build on
existing profiles instead of having to
copy and create new ones and for the
customizations the page customizations
there are new properties there are three
new properties of Interest here the the
clear layout clear actions and Clear
View and they do kind of what they say
the Clear layout clears all the layout
in the page and you'll have to read all
the fields that you feel are Irrelevant
for this page so it'll be empty to begin
with and then you add the additional
Fields clear actions does the same thing
clears all the actions in the page and
you'll have to add all the actions that
are should be available to the user and
for list Pages you can also use the
clear views to clear all the existing
views use one caveat though if you try
to use one of these clear methods on a
page customization that is used in a
roll
customization then you'll get an error
like this scenario here we try to use
the clear layout in this page
customization and then this profile
extension over here will start
failing let's undo that again so we
don't have to look at that
error okay moving on to query for
queries you can now add tool tips the
tool tips will help your users
understand what the data is used for and
how they should read it also of course
it supports tool tip
ml queries can now also be saved as Json
this allows you to easily send data back
and forth as
Json interfaces has gone through quite a
lot you can now extend interfaces so
instead of having to move to a complete
new interface you can now build on top
of an existing interface and expand it
with more
methods there are new keywords is and S
there's a whole session for working with
uh interfaces go check that out it's
very interesting to see what we can do
now with interfaces and how that can
build the modelization and modular code
base of the
future as part of the work with
interfaces we've add list of interfaces
in the last release we added list of in
and outstream and file upload and now we
extended with the list of interfaces
naturally the next thing is to have a
list of code units so we also added that
one and as you can see here it's easy to
Loop through a a list of uh code units
and use them in an interface with a
simple casting here if you try to assign
a a code unit to an interface that
doesn't Implement that interface then
obviously you would get an error as we
see here it cannot be converted
moving on to some more interesting stuff
for the people working with dates and
times we have to ask ourselves every now
and then if it is Friday in Al we can
ask if it's Friday like this this is how
we've been doing it for many years now
we have additional properties on the
date date time and time types that will
allow us to make much easier logic here
in this case we can ask if it's the
fifth day so the day of week is five
then it's Friday and we can find the
values of the day of week here on the
the net site for the system day a week
type we can do lots more with these
types we can ask uh about the month and
the day and the year if we want to do
some more complicated calculations here
on whether or not it's Friday and of
course we can always ask ourselves if
it's time to go have a drink and you can
look at the hour the minute the second
and the millisecond on the time
types let's look at the last part here
so we've added this to the language this
is a self reference so with this you can
reference the object that you're
currently in in this case I am in a code
unit I'm in a code unit so I can pass
myself on to another
function I can also use this to qualify
variables in this case I have a
parameter called variable but I also
have a code unit variable called
variable so I can qualify this one by
adding this to it and now we can easily
see that this variable here is no longer
used because I qualified this one to be
referencing this variable
instead there is a code analyzer if you
want to force this prefixes for wherever
it's needed you can choose to add it to
your uh code rules default it's hidden
but it will give you a code action that
has the ability to change for a single
instance and of course for document
project and workspace as we are getting
used to for these code fixes clicking it
for this instance we'll just add this to
the property here okay a brand new thing
in this release is the resources there's
a new method under the nav app type
called get Source taking in a resource
name and a stream that you want to have
the resource data in there's a whole
session on that also go check that out
it's a very interesting feature that
will help you ship Resources with your
app for those of you who are Keen at
spotting differences between versions
you'll find that there's a new method in
the session information type called AI
tokens used also a part of our effort to
do more AI so not quite ready yet for
consumption and you'll get an error like
the other one we saw earlier that this
one is not ready for use yet so more to
come
later for the HP client there's a new
method you can now do patch
easily and the patch is the update part
of a crot operation uh where you can
send a Delta of changes to a service and
then it will apply those to the resource
that you're trying to
patch this is just an easy way to get to
that method uh so that will help you
build simple Logic for
that let's end on something that may be
controversial for some the turn are
operator has been added to the a
language it's very common in many
languages and it has a way of
simplifying the if else
statements uh it it consists of a
condition and then something to do if it
it's true and something to do if it's
false so if we look at this code here we
can see classic if statement here if we
have some State then the expression is
unfavorable and we can see the use of
Turner operator here where we say the
style is if some state is closed then if
that's true then it's favorable if it's
false then it's ambiguous so here I
condensed the if statement into a single
line instead of having if it's Clos and
favorable else ambiguous right
of course this can quickly become very
convoluted if you misuse it and here's a
small example that uh doesn't even show
how complicated it can be but it does
show that it can quickly become quite
complicated if we look at this statement
here at the bottom line if it's blocked
then it's unfavorable if it's closed
then it's favorable otherwise ambiguous
just three statements here or three
different values here can make this line
unreadable or at least difficult to read
for new people so use this feature with
some consideration and with some thought
on how to maintain code in the future
the tary operator can be very powerful
if you use it right on that Cliffhanger
thank you for watching I hope you
enjoyed it